Well, I have a big announcement to make today,
حسناً، لدي خبر مهم أعلنه لكم اليوم.
and I'm really excited about this.
وأنا لذلك سعيد جداً.
And this may be a little bit of a surprise
وقد يكون هذا نوعاً ما مفاجئاً
to many of you who know my research
للعديد منكم الذين يعرفون جيداً طبيعة بحثي
and what I've done well.
وما قد أنجزته.
I've really tried to solve some big problems:
حاولت حقاً حل بعض المشاكل الكبيرة:
counterterrorism, nuclear terrorism,
مكافحة الإرهاب، والإرهاب النووي،
and health care and diagnosing and treating cancer,
والرعاية الصحية، وتشخيص ومعالجة السرطان،
but I started thinking about all these problems,
ولكنني بدأت أفكر بكل هذه المشاكل،
and I realized that the really biggest problem we face,
وأدركت أن أكبر مشكلة تواجهنا حقاً
what all these other problems come down to,
والتي تقل أهمية المشاكل الأخرى أمامها
is energy, is electricity, the flow of electrons.
هي الطاقة، الكهرباء، تدفق الالكترونات.
And I decided that I was going to set out
وقررت أنني سأبدأ
to try to solve this problem.
بمحاولة حل هذه المشكلة.
And this probably is not what you're expecting.
وربما لا يكون هذا ما تتوقعون.
You're probably expecting me to come up here
ربما تتوقعون مني أن اصعد إلى هنا
and talk about fusion,
وأتحدث عن الاندماج النووي،
because that's what I've done most of my life.
لأن ذلك ما فعلته طوال معظم حياتي.
But this is actually a talk about, okay --
ولكن في الحقيقة هذا حديث عن، حسناً--
(Laughter) —
(ضحك) --
but this is actually a talk about fission.
ولكن في الحقيقة هذا حديث عن الاندماج النووي.
It's about perfecting something old,
إنه عن صقل شيء قديم،
and bringing something old into the 21st century.
وإحضار شيء قديم إلى القرن الواحد العشرين.
Let's talk a little bit about how nuclear fission works.
دعونا نتحدث قليلاً عن كيف يعمل الاندماج النووي.
In a nuclear power plant, you have
في محطة الطاقة النووية، يكون لديك
a big pot of water that's under high pressure,
وعاء كبير من الماء تحت ضغط عالي،
and you have some fuel rods,
ويكون لديك بعض قضبان الوقود،
and these fuel rods are encased in zirconium,
وقضبان الوقود هذه مغطاة بالزركونيوم،
and they're little pellets of uranium dioxide fuel,
وهي كريات صغيرة من وقود ثاني أكسيد اليورانيوم،
and a fission reaction is controlled and maintained at a proper level,
ويُسيطر على التفاعل الانشطاري ويُحافظ عليه عند مستوى مناسب،
and that reaction heats up water,
وذلك التفاعل يُسخن الماء،
the water turns to steam, steam turns the turbine,
والماء يتحول إلى بخار، والبخار يحرك محرك التوربين،
and you produce electricity from it.
وتنتج الكهرباء منه.
This is the same way we've been producing electricity,
هذه هي نفس الطريقة التي ننتج بها الكهرباء،
the steam turbine idea, for 100 years,
فكرة بخار التوربين ولمدة 100 عام
and nuclear was a really big advancement
وكانت الطاقة النووية تطور كبير فعلاً
in a way to heat the water,
كطريقة لتسخين الماء
but you still boil water and that turns to steam and turns the turbine.
ولكنك ماتزال تحتاج إلى تسخين الماء الذي يتحول إلى بخار والبخار يحرك التوربين.
And I thought, you know, is this the best way to do it?
وفكرت هل هذه أفضل طريقة لعمل ذلك؟
Is fission kind of played out,
هل تقنية الانشطار النووي استنفدت بشكل ما
or is there something left to innovate here?
أم أن هناك شيء لم يُطور؟
And I realized that I had hit upon something
وأدركت أنني اكتشفت أمراً ما
that I think has this huge potential to change the world.
والذي يمتلك امكانية كبيرة لتغيير العالم.
And this is what it is.
وهذا هو ما هو عليه.
This is a small modular reactor.
هذا مفاعل صغير يحتوي على وحدات.
So it's not as big as the reactor you see in the diagram here.
ولذا هو ليس كبيراً كالمفاعل الذي ترونه في الرسم البياني هنا.
This is between 50 and 100 megawatts.
هذا بين 50 و 100 ميغاواط.
But that's a ton of power.
ولكن ذلك طن من القوة.
That's between, say at an average use,
وذلك مع الاستخدام المتوسط
that's maybe 25,000 to 100,000 homes could run off that.
يمكن ان يدير من 25,000 إلى 100,000 منزل .
Now the really interesting thing about these reactors
الآن الشيء المثير للاهتمام حقاً بخصوص هذه المفاعلات
is they're built in a factory.
هو أنها بُنيت في مصنع.
So they're modular reactors that are built
إذن هذه مفاعلات ذات وحدات مبنية
essentially on an assembly line,
بشكل أساسي على خط تجميع،
and they're trucked anywhere in the world,
وتشحن إلى أي مكان في العالم،
you plop them down, and they produce electricity.
تجمعهم فينتجون كهرباء.
This region right here is the reactor.
هذا القسم هنا هو المفاعل.
And this is buried below ground, which is really important.
وهذا يدفن تحت الأرض، وذلك أمرٌ مهم فعلاً.
For someone who's done a lot of counterterrorism work,
بالنسبة إلى شخص قام بالكثير من العمل في مجال مكافحة الارهاب،
I can't extol to you
لا يكنني أن أطري لكم
how great having something buried below the ground is
كم هو رائع دفن شيئاً ما تحت الأرض
for proliferation and security concerns.
من أجل الأسلحة النووية والمخاوف الأمنية.
And inside this reactor is a molten salt,
و في داخل هذا المفاعل يوجد ملح منصهر
so anybody who's a fan of thorium,
اي شخص مهتم بالثوريوم
they're going to be really excited about this,
سوف يتحمس كثيراً للموضوع
because these reactors happen to be really good
لأن هذه المفاعلات تصبح جيدة حقاً
at breeding and burning the thorium fuel cycle,
باستنسال و احراق دورة وقود الثوريوم
uranium-233.
يورانيوم - 233
But I'm not really concerned about the fuel.
لكنني لست متحفظ حقا" حول الوقود
You can run these off -- they're really hungry,
يمكنك التخلص من الوقود بالتشغيل، لدى المفاعلات نهم كبير للوقود
they really like down-blended weapons pits,
انها حقاً مثل الأسلحة الممزوجة في حفر
so that's highly enriched uranium and weapons-grade plutonium
انه يورانيوم عالي التخصيب و بلوتونيوم من درجة صنع السلاح
that's been down-blended.
تم مزجه بالأسفل
It's made into a grade where it's not usable for a nuclear weapon,
انه مصنوع في درجة لايمكن فيها استخدامه في سلاح نووي
but they love this stuff.
بل أنهم يحبون هذه الأشياء.
And we have a lot of it sitting around,
ولدينا الكثير من ذلك يجلس حولها،
because this is a big problem.
لأن هذه مشكلة كبيرة.
You know, in the Cold War, we built up this huge arsenal
تعلمون، في الحرب الباردة، بنينا هذه الترسانة الضخمة
of nuclear weapons, and that was great,
من الأسلحة النووية، كان ذلك عظيماً،
and we don't need them anymore,
ونحن لا حاجة لنا إليها بعد الآن،
and what are we doing with all the waste, essentially?
وماذا نحن فاعلون بجميع النفايات، أساسا؟
What are we doing with all the pits of those nuclear weapons?
ماذا نفعل مع جميع الحفر لتلك الأسلحة النووية؟
Well, we're securing them, and it would be great
حسنا، نقوم بتأمينها، وسيكون أمرا رائعا
if we could burn them, eat them up,
لو كنا نستطيع احراقها, استهلاكها
and this reactor loves this stuff.
وهذا المفاعل يحب هذه الأشياء.
So it's a molten salt reactor. It has a core,
لذا هو مفاعل ملح المنصهر. لديه نواة،
and it has a heat exchanger from the hot salt,
و لديه مبدل سخونة من الملح الساخن
the radioactive salt, to a cold salt which isn't radioactive.
الملح المشع، إلى ملح بارد غير مشعة.
It's still thermally hot but it's not radioactive.
لا يزال ساخن حرارياً ولكن ليس مشع.
And then that's a heat exchanger
ثم أن ذلك مبدل حراري
to what makes this design really, really interesting,
لما يجعل هذا التصميم حقاً، حقاً مثير للاهتمام،
and that's a heat exchanger to a gas.
وهذا مبدل حراري الى غاز.
So going back to what I was saying before about all power
اذاً، بالرجوع لما كنت أقوله من قبل حول كامل الطاقة
being produced -- well, other than photovoltaic --
التي يتم انتاجها، حسناً ، بخلاف الطاقة الكهروضوئية
being produced by this boiling of steam and turning a turbine,
الذي يجري انتاجه بغلي البخار و تدوير العنفة
that's actually not that efficient, and in fact,
وهذا في الواقع غير فعال، و بالواقع
in a nuclear power plant like this,
في محطة للطاقة النووية مثل هذه،
it's only roughly 30 to 35 percent efficient.
هو فقط فعال من 30 الى 35 بالمئة تقريباً
That's how much thermal energy the reactor's putting out
وهذا هو مقدار الطاقة الحرارية التي يقوم المفاعل باخمادها
to how much electricity it's producing.
إلى مقدار الكهرباء المنتجة.
And the reason the efficiencies are so low is these reactors
والكفاءات متدنية جداً والسبب هو هذه المفاعلات
operate at pretty low temperature.
وتعمل في درجات حرارة منخفضة جداً.
They operate anywhere from, you know,
أنها تعمل مابين، كما تعلمون،
maybe 200 to 300 degrees Celsius.
ربما من 200 إلى 300 درجة مئوية.
And these reactors run at 600 to 700 degrees Celsius,
و تعمل هذه المفاعلات عند درجة 600 إلى 700 درجة مئوية،
which means the higher the temperature you go to,
مما يعني أن أعلى درجة الحرارة تصلها
thermodynamics tells you that you will have higher efficiencies.
الديناميكية الحرارية تخبرك بأنه سيكون لديك فعالية أعلى
And this reactor doesn't use water. It uses gas,
وهذا المفاعل لا يستخدم المياه. بل يستخدم الغاز،
so supercritical CO2 or helium,
لذا فوق العتبة الحرجة ل CO2 أو حتى الهيليوم،
and that goes into a turbine,
يذهب ذلك إلى عنفه،
and this is called the Brayton cycle.
وهذا ما يسمى دورة برايتون.
This is the thermodynamic cycle that produces electricity,
وهذه الدورة الحرارية التي تنتج الكهرباء،
and this makes this almost 50 percent efficient,
وهذا ما يجعل ذلك 50% فعال تقريبا ،
between 45 and 50 percent efficiency.
ما بين 45 و 50 في المئة فعالية.
And I'm really excited about this,
وأنا متحمس جداً حول هذا الموضوع،
because it's a very compact core.
لأنه لب مدمج جداً
Molten salt reactors are very compact by nature,
مفاعلات الملح المنصهر مدمجة للغاية في طبيعتها،
but what's also great is you get a lot more electricity out
ولكن ما هو أيضا عظيم أن تحصل على الكثير من الكهرباء
for how much uranium you're fissioning,
قدر الكمية المنشطرة من اليورانيوم
not to mention the fact that these burn up.
ناهيك عن حقيقة أن هذا يتم احراقه
Their burn-up is much higher.
ان احتراقه هو أعلى بكثير
So for a given amount of fuel you put in the reactor,
حيث أنه بكمية معينة من الوقود المستخدم في المفاعل
a lot more of it's being used.
الكثير منه يتم استخدامه
And the problem with a traditional nuclear power plant like this
والمشكلة مع محطة تقليدية للطاقة النووية مثل هذه
is, you've got these rods that are clad in zirconium,
هي أنه لديك تلك القضبان مكسوة بالزركونيوم
and inside them are uranium dioxide fuel pellets.
وداخلها يوجد كريات وقود ثاني أكسيد اليورانيوم.
Well, uranium dioxide's a ceramic,
حسنا، ثاني أكسيد اليورانيوم هو سيراميك،
and ceramic doesn't like releasing what's inside of it.
و السيراميك لا يسمح بتحرير ما بداخله
So you have what's called the xenon pit,
اذاً لديك ما يسمى بحفرة زينون،
and so some of these fission products love neutrons.
وحتى أن بعض نواتج الأنشطار تميل النيوترونات.
They love the neutrons that are going on
انها تحب النيوترونات الجارية
and helping this reaction take place.
ويساعد هذا التفاعل على الحدوث.
And they eat them up, which means that, combined with
يستهلكونها كلها، مما يعني، أنه جنباً مع
the fact that the cladding doesn't last very long,
حقيقة أن الكسوة لا تدوم لفترة طويلة جداً،
you can only run one of these reactors
يمكنك فقط تشغيل واحد من هذه المفاعلات
for roughly, say, 18 months without refueling it.
لأقول تقريبا، 18 شهرا دون إعادة التزود بالوقود .
So these reactors run for 30 years without refueling,
اذاً، يتم تشغيل هذه المفاعلات لمدة 30 عاماً دون إعادة التزود بالوقود،
which is, in my opinion, very, very amazing,
وهو، في رأيي، مذهلة جداً،
because it means it's a sealed system.
لأنه يعني أنه نظام مغلق.
No refueling means you can seal them up
عدم التزويد بالوقود يعني أنه بامكانك ختمهم
and they're not going to be a proliferation risk,
وأنهم لن يشكلو خطر للانتشار،
and they're not going to have
وأنها لن يكون لها
either nuclear material or radiological material
اياً من المواد النووية أو المواد الإشعاعية
proliferated from their cores.
انتشرت من داخلهم.
But let's go back to safety, because everybody
ولكن دعونا نذهب مرة أخرى إلى الأمان، لأن الجميع
after Fukushima had to reassess the safety of nuclear,
بعد فوكوشيما اعادوا تقييم السلامة النووية
and one of the things when I set out to design a power reactor
ومن بين الأمور التي عندما كنت أقوم بتصميم مفاعل الطاقة
was it had to be passively and intrinsically safe,
كان أنه لابد أن تكون آمنة بشكل أساسي
and I'm really excited about this reactor
وأنا متحمس فعلا لهذا المفاعل
for essentially two reasons.
لسببين أساسيين
One, it doesn't operate at high pressure.
واحد، أنه لا يعمل بضغط عالي
So traditional reactors like a pressurized water reactor
حيث أن المفاعلات التقليدية كمفاعل الماء المضغوط
or boiling water reactor, they're very, very hot water
أو مفاعل الماء المغلي، هي ماء عالي السخونة
at very high pressures, and this means, essentially,
في ضغوط عالية جداً، وهذا يعني، أساسا،
in the event of an accident, if you had any kind of breach
في حالة وقوع حادث، إذا كان لديك أي نوع خرق
of this stainless steel pressure vessel,
بوعاء الضغط الفولاذي المقاوم للصدأ
the coolant would leave the core.
فان المبرد سيترك اللب
These reactors operate at essentially atmospheric pressure,
هذه المفاعلات تعمل عند الضغط الجوي أساسا،
so there's no inclination for the fission products
حيث لا يكون هناك أي ميل لنواتج الأنشطار
to leave the reactor in the event of an accident.
لترك المفاعل في حالة وقوع حادث.
Also, they operate at high temperatures,
أيضا، أنها تعمل في درجات حرارة عالية،
and the fuel is molten, so they can't melt down,
والوقود منصهر، حيث أنها لا يمكن أن تذوب إلى أسفل،
but in the event that the reactor ever went out of tolerances,
ولكن في حالة ما إذا تم تحميل المفاعل اكثر من طاقته
or you lost off-site power in the case
أو فقدت الطاقة خارج الموقع في حال
of something like Fukushima, there's a dump tank.
وقع شيء كفوكوشيما، يوجد خزان تفريغ
Because your fuel is liquid, and it's combined with your coolant,
نظراً لأن الوقود الخاص بك سائل، يقترن بسائل التبريد الخاص بك،
you could actually just drain the core
يمكنك فعلا استنزاف الداخل
into what's called a sub-critical setting,
إلى ما يسمى إعداد عتبة ما دون الحرجة،
basically a tank underneath the reactor
أساسا الخزان الذي أسفل المفاعل
that has some neutrons absorbers.
يحتوي على بعض ممتصي النيوترونات.
And this is really important, because the reaction stops.
وهذا المهم حقاً، لأن التفاعل يتوقف.
In this kind of reactor, you can't do that.
في مفاعل كهذا، لا يمكنك فعل ذلك.
The fuel, like I said, is ceramic inside zirconium fuel rods,
الوقود، كما قلت، هو سيراميك داخل قضبان وقود الزركونيوم،
and in the event of an accident in one of these type of reactors,
وفي حالة وقوع حادث في أحد أنواع المفاعلات كهذه ،
Fukushima and Three Mile Island --
فوكوشيما وثري مايل آيلند-
looking back at Three Mile Island, we didn't really see this for a while —
إذا نظرنا إلى الوراء في ثري مايل آيلند، لم نرى هذا حقاً لفترة من الوقت –
but these zirconium claddings on these fuel rods,
ولكن اكساء الزركونيوم على قضبان الوقود هذه ،
what happens is, when they see high pressure water,
ما يحدث، عندما يرون ارتفاع ضغط المياه،
steam, in an oxidizing environment,
بخار، في بيئة مؤكسدة،
they'll actually produce hydrogen,
هي في الواقع تنتج الهيدروجين،
and that hydrogen has this explosive capability
وأن هذا الهيدروجين لديه قدرة تفجيرية
to release fission products.
للإفراج عن منتجات الأنشطار.
So the core of this reactor, since it's not under pressure
فجوهر هذا المفاعل، منذ أنه ليس تحت ضغط
and it doesn't have this chemical reactivity,
وأنه لا يملك هذا التفاعل الكيميائي،
means that there's no inclination for the fission products
يعني أنه لا يوجد أي ميل لنواتج الأنشطار
to leave this reactor.
لترك هذا المفاعل.
So even in the event of an accident,
بل وحتى في حالة وقوع حادث،
yeah, the reactor may be toast, which is, you know,
نعم، قد يكون المفاعل تعطل، و، كما تعلمون،
sorry for the power company,
عذراً لشركة الكهرباء،
but we're not going to contaminate large quantities of land.
ولكننا لن نلوث كميات كبيرة من الأراضي.
So I really think that in the, say,
لذلك أعتقد حقاً أن في، فلنقل،
20 years it's going to take us to get fusion
سوف تأخذنا 20 عاماً للحصول على الانصهار
and make fusion a reality,
و جعل الانصهار حقيقة
this could be the source of energy
يمكن أن يكون هذا مصدرا للطاقة
that provides carbon-free electricity.
هذا يوفر كهرباء خالية من الكربون.
Carbon-free electricity.
الكهرباء خالية من الكربون.
And it's an amazing technology because
انها تقنية مذهلة لأن
not only does it combat climate change,
ليس فقط لمكافحة تغير المناخ،
but it's an innovation.
ولكنها ابتكار.
It's a way to bring power to the developing world,
أنها طريقة لإيصال الطاقة إلى العالم النامي،
because it's produced in a factory and it's cheap.
نظراً لأنها تنتج في مصنع وأنها رخيصة.
You can put them anywhere in the world you want to.
يمكنك وضعها في أي مكان تريده في العالم .
And maybe something else.
وربما شيء آخر.
As a kid, I was obsessed with space.
عندما كنت طفلاً كان لدي هاجس بالفضاء .
Well, I was obsessed with nuclear science too, to a point,
حسنا، كان لدي هاجس بالعلوم النووية أيضا، إلى حد ما،
but before that I was obsessed with space,
ولكن قبل ذلك كان لدي هاجس بالفضاء،
and I was really excited about, you know,
و كنت متحمساً حقاً ب ...
being an astronaut and designing rockets,
أن أكون رائد فضاء و أن أصمم الصواريخ
which was something that was always exciting to me.
وهو الأمر الذي كان دائماً مثيراً بالنسبة لي.
But I think I get to come back to this,
ولكن أعتقد أنه يجب أن أعود إلى هذا،
because imagine having a compact reactor in a rocket
لأنه تخيل وجود مفاعل مدمج في صاروخ
that produces 50 to 100 megawatts.
حيث ينتج من 50 إلى 100 ميغاوات.
That is the rocket designer's dream.
وهذا هو حلم مصمم الصاروخ .
That's someone who is designing a habitat on another planet's dream.
هذا شخص يقوم بتصميم موطن على حلم كوكب آخر
Not only do you have 50 to 100 megawatts
ليس فقط لديك 50 إلى 100 ميغاوات
to power whatever you want to provide propulsion to get you there,
لتزود بالطاقة لما تريد أن يقوم بالدفع ليوصلك الى هناك
but you have power once you get there.
ولكن لديك الطاقة بمجرد الوصول إلى هناك.
You know, rocket designers who use solar panels
تعلمون، مصممي الصاروخ الذي يستخدمون الألواح الشمسية
or fuel cells, I mean a few watts or kilowatts --
أو خلايا الوقود، أعني القليل من واط أو كيلوواط-
wow, that's a lot of power.
نجاح باهر، هذا يشكل الكثير من الطاقة.
I mean, now we're talking about 100 megawatts.
أعني، الآن نحن نتحدث حوالي 100 ميغاوات.
That's a ton of power.
وهذا طن من الطاقة.
That could power a Martian community.
يمكن لذلك تزويد المجتمع المريخي بالطاقة
That could power a rocket there.
ويمكنه أن يزود صاروخ بالطاقة هناك.
And so I hope that
ولذا فإنني أمل أن
maybe I'll have an opportunity to kind of explore
ربما سآخذ فرصة لنوع من استكشاف
my rocketry passion at the same time that I explore my nuclear passion.
شغفي الصاروخي في نفس الوقت الذي أقوم فيه باستكشاف شغفي النووي.
And people say, "Oh, well, you've launched this thing,
والناس يقولون، "أوه، حسنا، لقد أطلقت هذا الشيء،
and it's radioactive, into space, and what about accidents?"
وهو مشع، في الفضاء، وماذا حول الحوادث "؟
But we launch plutonium batteries all the time.
ولكن نطلق بطاريات البلوتونيوم طوال الوقت.
Everybody was really excited about Curiosity,
الجميع كان متحمس حقا" للفضول،
and that had this big plutonium battery on board
وأن كانت هذه بطارية كبيرة من البلوتونيوم على متنه
that has plutonium-238,
يحتوي على البلوتونيوم-238،
which actually has a higher specific activity
التي بالواقع لها نشاط محدد أعلى
than the low-enriched uranium fuel of these molten salt reactors,
من وقود اليورانيوم المنخفض التخصيب لمفاعلات الملح المنصهر هذه،
which means that the effects would be negligible,
مما يعني أن الآثار ستكون ضئيلة،
because you launch it cold,
لأنك أطلقته بارد،
and when it gets into space is where you actually activate this reactor.
وعندما يصل الى الفضاء, بالواقع هو المكان الذي تقوم بتنشيط هذا المفاعل .
So I'm really excited.
أنا متحمس حقاً.
I think that I've designed this reactor here
وأعتقد أنني قمت بتصميم هذا المفاعل هنا
that can be an innovative source of energy,
يمكن أن يكون مصدر مبتكر للطاقة،
provide power for all kinds of neat scientific applications,
توفير الطاقة لجميع أنواع التطبيقات العلمية الأنيقة،
and I'm really prepared to do this.
وأنا على استعداد حقاً للقيام بذلك.
I graduated high school in May, and --
تخرجت في المدرسة الثانوية في أيار/مايو، و--
(Laughter) (Applause) —
(ضحك) (تصفيق) –
I graduated high school in May,
تخرجت في المدرسة الثانوية في أيار/مايو،
and I decided that I was going to start up a company
وقد قررت أن أقوم بإنشاء شركة
to commercialize these technologies that I've developed,
لتسويق هذه التكنولوجيات التي طورتها،
these revolutionary detectors for scanning cargo containers
هذه كاشفات ثورية لتفحص حاويات الشحن
and these systems to produce medical isotopes,
وهذه النظم لإنتاج النظائر الطبية،
but I want to do this, and I've slowly been building up
ولكن أريد أن أفعل هذا، ولقد قمت بالتطور ببطء
a team of some of the most incredible people
فريق من بعض الناس المذهلين جدا"
I've ever had the chance to work with,
كانت لي الفرصة أكثر من أي وقت مضى للعمل معهم
and I'm really prepared to make this a reality.
وأنا على استعداد حقاً لجعل هذا حقيقة واقعة.
And I think, I think, that looking at the technology,
وأعتقد، أعتقد أن النظر الى التكنولوجيا،
this will be cheaper than or the same price as natural gas,
هذا سوف يكون أرخص أو نفس سعرالغاز الطبيعي ،
and you don't have to refuel it for 30 years,
و لا تحتاج لاعادة التزود بالوقود لمدة 30 عاماً
which is an advantage for the developing world.
وهو منفعة للعالم النامي.
And I'll just say one more maybe philosophical thing
و سوف أقول شئ آخر ربما فلسفي أكثر
to end with, which is weird for a scientist.
لانهي به، وهو غريب للعالم.
But I think there's something really poetic
ولكن أعتقد أن هناك حقاً شيئا شعري
about using nuclear power to propel us to the stars,
حول استخدام الطاقة النووية لدفعنا إلى النجوم،
because the stars are giant fusion reactors.
لأن النجوم هي مفاعلات انشطارية عملاقة.
They're giant nuclear cauldrons in the sky.
أنها مراجل نووية عملاقة في السماء.
The energy that I'm able to talk to you today,
الطاقة التي باستطاعتي أن أتحدث إليكم اليوم عنها،
while it was converted to chemical energy in my food,
وفي حين أنه تم تحويلها إلى طاقة كيميائية في طعامي،
originally came from a nuclear reaction,
جاءت أصلاً من تفاعل نووي،
and so there's something poetic about, in my opinion,
حيث يوجد شي شعري حول..في رأيي
perfecting nuclear fission
إتقان الأنشطار النووي
and using it as a future source of innovative energy.
واستخدامه كمصدر مستقبلي للطاقة الابتكارية.
So thank you guys.
لذا شكرا يا رفاق.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)